<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>zesrajsie.tk</title>
	<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/tags/linux/</link>
	<description>Recent content in linux on zesrajsie.tk</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 20:55:32 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://zesrajsie.tk/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>You DON&#39;T NEED a good PC</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/goodpc/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 21:47:40 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/goodpc/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s a simple way to have more money. for free!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-do-you-need&#34;&gt;What do you need?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we need to specify how we use computers.
Here are some of the more performance-heavy things that people use PCs for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio / Video / Image Editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gaming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Browsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text Editing / Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably could do all of these things on a 400$ box.
But how?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lower-you-expectations&#34;&gt;Lower you expectations.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, really.
The most important thing is to lower your expectations and stop fearing change.
You need to basically realize that you don&amp;rsquo;t need to play -  i don&amp;rsquo;t know, Soyberpunk 2077 with raytracing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But don&amp;rsquo;t fear, it is almost always the programmers fault!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let&amp;rsquo;s take Minecraft.
The OG edition of the game is written in java.
Because it was written in java in 2009, the game code runs mostly single-threaded and isn&amp;rsquo;t optimized.
When microsoft decided to make an UWP version of minecraft for windows 10, the xbox and mobile devices - they decided to rewrite the engine in C++.
The results are that in the java version of the game, the max. world render distance is 64 (with optimization mods!).
In the C++ version it&amp;rsquo;s the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it&amp;rsquo;s a small issue compared to&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;muh-heckin-web-browsers11&#34;&gt;mUh HeCkIn WeB bRoWsErS1!1!!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is safe to say it: the web is beyond repair.
The sites are bloated, the browsers are bloated, the languages are bloated.
EVERYTHING. IS. BLOATED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I genuinely think that without a decent PC you can&amp;rsquo;t browse the internet comfortably.
For example, Firefox starts up on my PC (it&amp;rsquo;s pretty beefy, even if the OS is installed on an HDD) in around 5 - 10 seconds.
In comparison - starting up Firefox on my Thinkpad x230 takes 30 seconds.
The worst thing is that there aren&amp;rsquo;t any browsers that are really faster and have good website support, and chromium has the same issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(yes, i know that surf exists, dont @ me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if web browsers were more optimized, they would still have high system requirements due to the web technologies themselves.
Websites really shouldn&amp;rsquo;t compile 25 megabytes of javascript.
If your site requires javascript to function - it probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a website.
Web developers should focus more on stripping down the javascript, not on making the site unusable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;so-how-to-actually-have-a-better-pc-for-free&#34;&gt;So how to actually have a better PC for free&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is required, and you won&amp;rsquo;t escape from it.
You can play almost every game on linux already (from my experience), so there aren&amp;rsquo;t any reasons to not jump ship.
Windows always was the most bloated OS on the market, and it&amp;rsquo;s mere existence is constantly pushing hardware manufacturers to release overpriced, power-hungry CPU&amp;rsquo;s and GPU&amp;rsquo;s.
As for my recommendation - if you want a huge performance boost, just install linux. I would suggest Linux Mint MATE edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(OPTIONAL) Install BSD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you got the balls to do it. do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize your OS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;on windows you really can&amp;rsquo;t truly optimize your system, so i&amp;rsquo;ll just explain what to do on UNIX-based systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install a more lightweight graphical environment.
For example if you use KDE, install XFCE. If you use XFCE, install a tiling window manager etc.
Configuring a tiling WM can be hard, but it will always be way faster than GNOME / KDE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you don&amp;rsquo;t mind wayland you could even use (for gaming) the gamescope compositor made by valve for the steam deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove unnecessary services running in the background
Get rid of plymouth, sshd and other stuff you don&amp;rsquo;t need, you could theoretically not use a display manager and instead use cli login with .bashrc xorg autostart.
It will basically save you ram, and maybe even CPU usage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop running other aplications while gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will greatly increase availible RAM.
Needed for 4GB (or less) ram systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower your resolution in games (if you can)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD&amp;rsquo;s FSR works on linux without any problems (you can enable it via lutris or in gamescope). if you have a 1920x1080 screen you could just upscale from 1280x720 or 1600x900.
It will increase performance with little loss of visual quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t enable the FPS counter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little psychological trick.
Just stop caring about the FPS and find the settings that you could play on, without setting the barrier to 60 fps or 30.
Most people could probably play comfortably in 48 fps, and in some games even 24 fps without even knowing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(OPTIONAL) Sell your PC and buy &amp;ldquo;a better one&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds stupid, but with experience you could buy some way better parts for the same price.
You could basically in a few weeks get a 20 - 50% performance boost just by picking your PC parts better.
Also you can just add a couple of bucks to your budget and buy a objectively better computer with a very small price increase (let&amp;rsquo;s say 20 - 50$).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;start-using-software-that-actually-cares-about-performance&#34;&gt;Start using software that actually cares about performance.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a ton of FOSS software that runs a lot better than all of it&amp;rsquo;s proprietary counterparts.
You&amp;rsquo;d be suprised that you could edit videos, do VFX, produce music and code comfortably on a 250$ box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of such software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D / VFX software:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natron&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video Editors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kdenlive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Olive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoutcut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handbrake (a media transcoding program)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music Production software / plugins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ardour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenMPT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Milkytracker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calf Plugins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux Studio Plugins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claudia Patchbay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carla Rack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graphics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GIMP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inkscape (for vector graphics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Krita (for drawing and 2D animation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code Blocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VS Codium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vim (dont beat me it&amp;rsquo;s a joke)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When i built my home server, it had a shit GPU (and 7$ Nvidia NVS 300)
I found out that even then it had decent performance in games like Half-Life 2 or Xonotic.
This inspired me to make that article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use your 10 dollar PCs, install gentoo and have fun getting max performance out from you computers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Linux gets Rusty: My Response</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxrust/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 20:55:32 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxrust/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;all i can say is: Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;oxidization&#34;&gt;Oxidization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;first, we need to look at the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is a new multi-paradigm programming language now commonly used for desktop applications and utilities.
It&amp;rsquo;s biggest &amp;ldquo;pros&amp;rdquo; are efficiency and memory safety.
For context i will just add that Rust is popular among the software development community.
Especially the more &amp;ldquo;Leftist&amp;rdquo; side of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux is implementing Rust simply because there aren&amp;rsquo;t as many C developers as one would think.
Most senior developers working on low-level code are now retired - or dead.
Every year people are stepping down from the kernel and moving on with their lives.
Basically - C is a dead language that zoomers are too afraid to learn, and the supply of people programming in it is quickly depleting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;blahaj-programmer-socks-and-rust&#34;&gt;Blahaj, Programmer Socks, and Rust&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s debunk Rust into oblivion, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is more efficient than its biggest competitor, C++ - at least in most cases.
It&amp;rsquo;s mostly because unlike C++ it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have garbage collection.
Instead it uses the concepts of &lt;em&gt;ownership&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;borrowing&lt;/em&gt;.
Ownership basically is a system in which memory is automatically freed when a variable is not needed.
This generally saves memory space, but increases CPU usage and can lead to some other problems.
In C, developer does this manually with the &lt;code&gt;free()&lt;/code&gt; function. Even if this is not needed in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, C is much faster, and modern C compilers can compile memory leak-less code without much trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memory Safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust fanboys think that it&amp;rsquo;s 100% memory safe. And it&amp;rsquo;s a lie.
Rust in no way guarantees memory safety.
The only difference between &amp;ldquo;unsafe&amp;rdquo; languages like C and rust, is that the Rust compiler flags unsafe code as errors that you need to correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-meme-debunk&#34;&gt;BONUS Meme debunk:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eVeRyThInG iS gOiNg To Be ReWrItTeN iN rUsT!!1!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust isn&amp;rsquo;t nearly as universal as most femboys on hacker news think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++ iS dEd!!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nah, people will still use C++ because of legacy compatibility and a ton C / C++ libraries that will never be usable with other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-kernel-of-c&#34;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;kernel&lt;/em&gt; of C&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, &lt;strong&gt;EXPERIMENTAL&lt;/strong&gt; Rust support is being added to the upcoming linux 6.1 release.
Most distributions will include Rust maybe in a year or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them will probably disable Rust support for some time after the 6.1 release, as it is currently optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;if-it-moves-compile-it&#34;&gt;If It Moves, Compile It&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest critic of Rust in the kernel is the time it takes to compile.
Another language in the build toolchain will basically make the kernel twice as heavy to run and build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux was historically a very lightweight kernel, despite of it&amp;rsquo;s monolithic nature.
Now it is becoming more and more bloated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this in my previous blog post, but corporate sponsors are one of the main reasons things like Rust get included in the kernel.
In a few years many people with low-end hardware will probably need to change their setup because of this change (and many others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, sticking to facts: soon compiling the kernel will take around 8 hours on mid-range hardware. imagine using gentoo with these compile times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;but-should-you&#34;&gt;But Should You?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for now i&amp;rsquo;ll try use linux even with all of this.
but in the future? i will probably switch to BSD.
even without some games, i should be fine with the linux binary compatibility.
idk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Datadesk: What is it?</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/datadesk/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 22:03:49 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/datadesk/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;The worst document format that exists, and why i made it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-tell-me-what-the-fuck-is-it&#34;&gt;But tell me: What the fuck is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Datadesk (DS) is an interpreted markup language that bridges the gap between images and text files.
Characters and sentences are placed by the user on a matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DS has 4 main commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/s - writes a sentence to the screen, automatically placing multiple lines until the end of the command (/e).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/r - draws a rectangle on the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/e - ends the /s command (and every command that has a dynamic argument number).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/  - used only once, &amp;ldquo;/&amp;rdquo; means the scene root in a datadesk source file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a line numbering argument for /s evoked by the letter &amp;ldquo;L&amp;rdquo; like this: &lt;code&gt;/sL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language uses a pass-based syntax in which the return key separates different passes.
This approach makes writing software with datadesk in mind really easy.
It works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st pass: the y coordinate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd pass: the x coordinate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3rd pass: the command / a character&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the 3rd pass is a command there are arguments after the pass; Technically these are called &amp;ldquo;Optional passes&amp;rdquo;.
The y coordinate is specified first because ncurses works the same way.
Even if it feels weird at first, it is really simple in the long run.
This decision makes sense because people first specify the row (y), and then the column (x).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-drawer-interpreter&#34;&gt;The DRAWER interpreter.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DRAWER (DRAWER Reference Alpha-stage Working without Errors and it&amp;rsquo;s Robust as fuck) interpreter, is a ncurses based DS interpreter made by me from scratch.
Currently it only has around 200 lines of code and it&amp;rsquo;s extremely minimal. You can use DRAWER with the following command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;drawer &amp;lt;path to the ds source file.ds&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The document is shown after the execution of that command, you can close the interpreter with F12.
&lt;code&gt;drawer -h&lt;/code&gt; shows you the version of drawer and cli arguments that you can use with it.
&lt;code&gt;drawer -d&lt;/code&gt; shows you a datadesk demo file containing some nice art, graphics etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;datadesk-the-sequel-what-will-follow-ds1&#34;&gt;Datadesk: The sequel (what will follow DS1?)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently planning on adding support on multiple pages in the same document and adding variables.
Maybe i will do things such as block quotes and support for slanted and bold text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DS3 will probably have some interactive elements added as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened-to-your-previous-project-allcom&#34;&gt;What happened to your previous project, allcom?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lost motivation and cancelled the game. That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Linux is dead (and we killed it)</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxsucks/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 21:57:30 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxsucks/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Look, it&amp;rsquo;s just my opinion. But Linux is truly dead.
It has become unstable, bloated and unusable. Even Windows beats most popular distros in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even &amp;ldquo;pro&amp;rdquo; distributions like Arch or Gentoo suffer from most of the problems that modern UNIX has.
An example that i like to use is NetworkManager, a truly useless piece of software.
This deamon really is just a workaround that makes systemd&amp;rsquo;s network system usable to your average Joe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other init-systems like openrc and runit just work.
Yes - they require a dhcp service (if you even use dhcp) - but even then these init systems ship with at least working network setup tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s analyze the downfall of Linux in detail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-desktop&#34;&gt;The Desktop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me it all started with GNOME 3.
I know I sound stupid because everyone bullies GNOME and systemd, but hear me out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GNOME 2 was perfect.
Ok, maybe not. Still it was really close to perfection. Why?
It was easy to use, stable and customizable - everything you want from a desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, from nowhere - gnome 3 appeared.
They have scrapped everything they built since the 90s and started from scratch.
And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a success, actually, it was the Windows Vista of linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone came to my house with a gun and said &amp;ldquo;describe what gnome 3 in 2011 was in 5 seconds or i&amp;rsquo;ll shoot you&amp;rdquo; i would say that it was janky, very janky.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand why the dev-team did this, and i don&amp;rsquo;t understand it now.
After some time the GNOME team fixed their desktop, and it was actually pretty easy to use.
Most popular distributions like ubuntu returned to their roots with shipping gnome again.
But while all of this was happening, gnome 3 was the literal definition of a &amp;ldquo;dumpster fire&amp;rdquo; under the hood.
Through time the team added too many unneceseary features to gnome and added systemd dependencies.
Because of the popularity of systemd, no one saw this as a problem. But it really is.
Now with GNOME 42 using 2 gigs idling i can confortably say that it won&amp;rsquo;t ever go back to it&amp;rsquo;s days of glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KDE had gone a simillar route, but with a happier ending overall.
KDE 3 was the best alternative to GNOME 2, and the most customizable desktop of it&amp;rsquo;s time.
In 2008 / 2009 KDE 4 was released. And you guessed it - it was a total disaster.
Everybody hated this thing, it was barely usable. At least GNOME 3 didn&amp;rsquo;t crashed almost every time you wanted to change a theme.
The succesor to KDE 4, Plasma is actually very successful to this day. It mostly reclaimed the desktop throne from KDE 3 / Trinity, and it is the favourite to this day.
But it didn&amp;rsquo;t protect KDE from it&amp;rsquo;s jank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;kde-plasma-jank-list&#34;&gt;KDE Plasma jank list&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a ton of confusing menus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QT5 is still a mess&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses even more ram than GNOME&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outdated widgets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature Creep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weird Design Choices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A shitty store app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broken, unfinished app suite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breeze theme is the only one that is actually usable and integrates with GTK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unpolished, buggy animations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bugs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even More Bugs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s end it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;systemd&#34;&gt;systemd&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the other side of our linux coin is &lt;strong&gt;systemd&lt;/strong&gt;, a linux init system that creeped into every distro since Debian 7 codenamed &amp;ldquo;Jessie&amp;rdquo;
Most people just don&amp;rsquo;t care enough about linux&amp;rsquo;s internal workings to hate systemd - it is still a usable and easy to use init system.
I know that it&amp;rsquo;s a meme, but systemd really is the most bloated PID1 that ever existed, having a ton of useless services that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even be there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-not-so-comprehensive-list-of-useless-soystemd-wonk-and-jank&#34;&gt;The not-so comprehensive list of useless soystemd wonk and jank&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-homed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-logind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-boot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd/Journal (yes, there are multiple naming conventions used there)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-sysusers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-nspawn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-stub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd.mount (another naming convention)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-fstab-generator (WHY, JUST WHY. &lt;code&gt;genfstab&lt;/code&gt; exists.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all of these systemd modules shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a part of the init system, but they somehow are&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from systemd&amp;rsquo;s disregard of the UNIX philosophy, it boots significantly slower than for example runit or s6 (at least on all of my machines).
It is really a beast, a performance hog and it simply just does too much. PID 1 should just start some services with dependency management and that&amp;rsquo;s it.
Another big thing that i hate is &lt;strong&gt;pulseaudio&lt;/strong&gt;, even if it is being currently replaced by pipewire (and that&amp;rsquo;s really good) - it is a wonky mess that never works,
uses too much system resources, isn&amp;rsquo;t system-wide, has horrible command-line interfaces and is just simply buggy.
We should stick to alsa in the long-term. Why?
It simply just works, yes - only after extensive configuration to let it work on modern browsers, add multi-channel support etc. - but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mentality of &lt;em&gt;Lennart Poettering&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; software is spreading too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-freedom-anyway&#34;&gt;What is Freedom anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freedom in linux is decaying.
Most people are forced to use pulseaudio (because of steam and other stuff), X.Org (wayland exists, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t as stable), systemd (because gnome) and other things.
In the early days of linux there really was more choice than now.
In the 90s and early 2000s, when UNIX systems came to your average Joe, people used BSDs, Linuxes, BeOS etc.
Now it&amp;rsquo;s just ubuntu and arch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People started realizing this and now some are moving to BSD or - if someone doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about privacy - MacOS.
I suspect that in a few years most popular linux distros will be closer to windows than to any free-software UNIX imaginable.
But let&amp;rsquo;s end this for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux users wanting it to be more &amp;ldquo;user-friendly&amp;rdquo; killed linux. Yes, it is more integrated - but at what cost?
GNOME 3 and systemd are the greatest examples of this trend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Piracy is 80% morally correct</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/piracy/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 21:51:54 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/piracy/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;this will be a controversial one&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-piracy-stealing&#34;&gt;Is Piracy Stealing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, not at all.
Unlike real piracy (a group of guys goes into a boat in the middle of the fucking ocean and steals everything) nothing just ceases to exist.
So technically it is just unauthorized file copying, which sounds stupid because everyone can copy files on their disk in any capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even then, let&amp;rsquo;s be honest.
Stealing (like real stealing) from big corporations doesn&amp;rsquo;t hurt them much + nobody cares about them (outside of the apple community where apple inc. is their lord and savior).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-that-20&#34;&gt;What about that 20%?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That 20% is mostly stuff that is already illegal, or it&amp;rsquo;s just immoral anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Porn (don&amp;rsquo;t coom kids.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Child Po- Cheese Pizza&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Why would you download this, yes downloading this stuff from torrent with a VPN is safe (kind of) but why?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some indie games made by a guy in his basement worth for five bucks (not talking about AAA&amp;rsquo;s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Like these people actually want to make something good, support them. But still &amp;ldquo;no tux, no bux&amp;rdquo; is a rule that i&amp;rsquo;ll follow.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bittorrent-protocol-itself&#34;&gt;The BitTorrent protocol itself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like torrents mostly because the BitTorrent protocol revolutionized the Internet.
It was created when your average internet connection was around 50 KB/s, and most people still used dial-up.
But why it was so revolutional?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it is very hard to shut down a torrent network - that&amp;rsquo;s why it is so commonly used for piracy and rare / lost media archival.
Back in the day most websites were owned by people, not companies. A side effect of this was that servers of a website could be shut down at any time due to many reasons. The creator of that site could be bored, forgot to turn on his server etc.
Obviously, when the servers are down, you cannot download stuff from this person. BitTorrent is decentralized, so everyone having the file on his own computer is a potential server. Only one person online (more popular torrents have even 50 people at the same time) can keep the torrent up and send the data to you.
Because of this decentralization, most companies can&amp;rsquo;t stop even a single torrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from that, download speeds of the files sent through torrent weren&amp;rsquo;t capped by the server, so these files could be downloaded with very high speeds.
These reasons are all i need to prefer torrent over anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-2-interwebz-pirate&#34;&gt;how 2 interwebz pirate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to know what is a torrent tracker.
A torrent tracker is a server that - as the name suggests - tracks peers across many torrent networks. Most of these trackers are aggregated and hosted on sites like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thepiratebay.org&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1337x.to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rutracker.org (it&amp;rsquo;s in russian, some basic language skills required to use it on a daily basis)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;these are sites that i prefer to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to download files from them? It&amp;rsquo;s easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to the website (example is from thepiratebay.org)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;search what you want&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click on it (and avoid ads when possible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click on the button with da magnet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;your client should appear and set up the torrent for you by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax and wait till the thing completes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;now you have your favourite music album, hentai game, or something else on your hard drive!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;Ending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was it, i hope this guide to torrents was useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Music</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/music/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 23:06:35 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/music/</guid>
		<description>&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/music.css&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;grid&#34;&gt;

        	&lt;div class=&#34;ibm_cp&#34;&gt;
				
			&lt;p&gt;ibm_cp (2021)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/ibmcp_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://anonfiles.com/j4WaV6Pdub/ibm_cp_zip&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;m4kulaturamusic&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;imagine fucking existing (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/imagine_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/lPo0AJzZ#9YHB3-lV5ygL159n9pKFjPj5xAReCyb4jb_5xMTDtyY&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;tracking&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;Tracking Devices (2021)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/trackingdevices_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/dG4TiaDK#OmE7ubjoY_R1O7QZY7FDNh9E7aY9XHSc6ohTeSd3qDM&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;house&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;Chastity House (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/chastityhouse_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/NXIzBSpQ#Bi1xgvVaHVjRpLa-4ULB5h_0ip0m6Pwx22AMyigjYJY&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Reserve</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/reserve/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:14:13 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/reserve/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-the-fuck-is-it&#34;&gt;What the fuck is it?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;m4kulatura&amp;rsquo;s private reserve (MPR) is a repository full of software, games, music and other stuff.
it is submitted by m4kulatura and his friends mostly for personal use and archival.
still, anyone with an internet connection can download files from the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;download-as-much-as-you-want&#34;&gt;download as much as you want!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http server: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ftp.whentheh.tk&#34;&gt;https://ftp.whentheh.tk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(currently inactive due to maintenance)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>M4kulatura</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/m4kulatura/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:01:17 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/m4kulatura/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura is the main character in the m4kulatura lore.
Basically the center-piece connecting everything together.
Working on his webiste and multiple other projects since 2016.
Oh and he also makes music: &lt;a href=&#34;https://makulaturka.tk/music&#34;&gt;https://makulaturka.tk/music&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;info&#34;&gt;Info:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Class: Boomer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sub-Class: Femboy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Age: 14 (as of now)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sex: Male (sadly)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orientation (sowwy fow le LGBT speek ;-;): asexual, heteroromantic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a boyfriend: nope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a girlfriend: nope. (oficially)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes to work: nope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes to school: yes, he goes to ZSTiE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;related-to&#34;&gt;Related to:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blueberry (best friend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DeusVult (2nd best friend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynio (coworker / friend)
tty7derty
askel
snybej
przeróbek
major
ballie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kosmitek (classmate)
Lewan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matteo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CartoonGuy (an old friend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sofeł (&lt;em&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s a long story&lt;/em&gt; / ex (?) )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura is the main maintainer of projects like WarpOS, TMS, MMS, datadesk and others.
He does it mostly for fun and to let his mind focus on things other than school and work.
Aside from maintaining these systems he has an average social life and composes music in his spare time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura a few years ago started talking to sofeł.
They were best friends for a few years, knowing everything about eachother and living their lives together.
Most people said that they were &lt;strong&gt;[REDACTED]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some time they broke up, this breakup caused a suicide attempt involving m4kulatura, as well as other issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura also has some controversial, right-wing political opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;likes&#34;&gt;Likes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old Tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic Games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Politics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low-Level Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hates&#34;&gt;Hates:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoomers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TikTok&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proprietary Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple Stans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LGBT+ Fandom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Furries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;annotations&#34;&gt;Annotations:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>wiki template</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/template/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:01:17 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/template/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;a basic summary&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;info&#34;&gt;Info:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;related-to&#34;&gt;Related to:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;more detailed info&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;likes&#34;&gt;Likes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hates&#34;&gt;Hates:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;annotations&#34;&gt;Annotations:&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Wikitest</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wikitest/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:01:17 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wikitest/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;esse mam z cb&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/about/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 21:54:15 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/about/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, i’m m4kulatura, your favourite dumbass and linux user from the hood. I usually do music and programming (mostly for UNIX systems).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-do-i-use&#34;&gt;What Do I Use?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OS: Void GNU/Linux 64-bit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desktop: GNOME 42&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web Browser: firefox&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image Editor: GIMP + Krita&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video Editor: Blender&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D art / 2D art / VFX: Blender&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music Stuff: Mostly MOD trackers + Ardour / Bitwig Studio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text / Code editor: Vim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hardware&#34;&gt;Hardware:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cellphone: Xiaomi Mi 10T Lite 5G&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Media Player: Astell&amp;amp;Kern AK70 MKII&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laptop: Thinkpad x230&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Headphones: AKG K712&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microphone: Crono Studio 101&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keyboard: SPC Gear GK630&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mouse: Glorious Model O + Razer Diamondback (original from 2005)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;pc-specs&#34;&gt;PC specs:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CPU: AMD Ryzen 5 3600&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPU: AMD Radeon 6600 XT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAM: 16GB DDR4 3200MHz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HDD / SSD: 500gb SSD; 500gb HDD; 2TB HDD;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Blog</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/blog/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 21:51:55 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/blog/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;My blog, i usually talk about technology, but i do other things as well.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-19T21:47:40&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 19&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/goodpc/&#34;&gt;You DON&amp;#39;T NEED a good PC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-10T20:55:32&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 10&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxrust/&#34;&gt;Linux gets Rusty: My Response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-06T22:03:49&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 06&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/datadesk/&#34;&gt;Datadesk: What is it?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-06T21:57:30&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 06&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxsucks/&#34;&gt;Linux is dead (and we killed it)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-06T21:51:54&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 06&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/piracy/&#34;&gt;Piracy is 80% morally correct&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>M4kulatura wiki</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 21:51:55 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the m4kulatura lore wiki, sadly it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated in a while.
Fortunately i&amp;rsquo;m currently working on it!
Feel free to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-09-22T22:01:17&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Sep 22&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/m4kulatura/&#34;&gt;M4kulatura&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-09-22T22:01:17&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Sep 22&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/template/&#34;&gt;wiki template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-09-22T22:01:17&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Sep 22&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/wikitest/&#34;&gt;Wikitest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
