<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>zesrajsie.tk</title>
	<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/tags/personal/</link>
	<description>Recent content in personal on zesrajsie.tk</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 19:48:15 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://zesrajsie.tk/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>Void Linux: a Year long review</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/voidlinux1year/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 20:13:52 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/voidlinux1year/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr: don&amp;rsquo;t use it&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Void Linux is one of those distros that you should probably setup on a secondary, low-powered machine that doesn&amp;rsquo;t run modern Windows very well. That is the best use for a &amp;ldquo;DIY&amp;rdquo; distro, after all. You set it up with your computer in mind to get maximum performance available, and then sit back and use it sometimes for watching movies, torrenting and other stuff like that - nothing serious. After using this distribution for a year, i am pretty confident that this is how void isa being developed and tested, and that most people don&amp;rsquo;t run it on their main machines. The height of the thinkpad meme (and i&amp;rsquo;m saying this as a person that actually bought a thinkpad, even though i don&amp;rsquo;t really need one and i use it only on trips occasionally, maybe in bed).
Too bad i decided to completely disregard it and install it on my main production machine i&amp;rsquo;m literally writing this on. Now i&amp;rsquo;m on openSUSE Tumbleweed, after over a year of using Void on this PC. Today i want to share my experience with Void, and highlight where it&amp;rsquo;s really good, and where it shits itself - which is arguably more important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-good&#34;&gt;The Good!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with what Void Linux does right, just to add some pint of optimism to this rant about the distro. At first i should mention that void is really fast. Like it&amp;rsquo;s one of the fastest distros i have ever used, better than even most of my arch setups. While it&amp;rsquo;s not optimized like gentoo, it&amp;rsquo;s good enough for most people. The kernel uses a reasonable configuration, but you might have problems with the realtek wi-fi drivers. I don&amp;rsquo;t know honestly, generally hardware support isn&amp;rsquo;t bad at all. The best thing about Void is probably the guided installer, which automatically installs the base OS so you can configure it. It kinda resembles systems like Slackware or even MS-DOS, making for a good compromise between modern graphical installation programs and the manual setup of Arch and Gentoo.
Also it&amp;rsquo;s fully in the command line, working even in secure shell and other environments where graphics aren&amp;rsquo;t a priority. Or to put it in a different way, the installer will still work without graphics drivers, it won&amp;rsquo;t crash on you.
You obviously can also use your system for recovery, but it&amp;rsquo;s not ideal. I&amp;rsquo;d rather use something like debian or even Ubuntu. XBPS is also a pretty good packaging system, it&amp;rsquo;s one of the more lightwieght ones, and it&amp;rsquo;s better than stuff you get in Arch and Debian for example. The only thing i&amp;rsquo;d want is a single feature from &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt;, the autoremove which automatically removes unnecessary dependencies. You CAN remove a package with all it&amp;rsquo;s redundant dependencies, but if you forget to uninstall it with &lt;code&gt;-R&lt;/code&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;re screwed, the dependencies stay on your system and you can easily forget about them.
Obviously i should state the obvious. This is a do it yourself distro, you can pick yourself every element of your system, like the desktop environment and most software. It&amp;rsquo;s generally a good balance between hellholes like gentoo and the ease of use (and rigidity) of stuff like Ubuntu or Manjaro.
But, that&amp;rsquo;s where the good parts end i think, the rest is really bad and infuriating, knowing how good this distribution could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bad&#34;&gt;The Bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s talk about the bad, infuriating, and truly crap parts of Void Linux. It can be really bad sometimes, so let&amp;rsquo;s just get into it.
First, runit is really confusing at parts, it&amp;rsquo;s nearly undocumented, so you can do something wrong and never recieve an error. It&amp;rsquo;s literally ed levels of feedback, and you often have to rely on your intuition with runit. The same goes for some features of the XBPS package manager. Also the packaging of some programs like GNOME is weird, providing outdated software and requiring additional setup, which is something that you&amp;rsquo;re never told about. The GDM package is really tricky for example. Another big problem are the repositories, which very often don&amp;rsquo;t have what you want, for example most proprietary apps like Discord, or the remote desktop tool Parsec. For some reason steam is in the main repos though. I don&amp;rsquo;t know why that&amp;rsquo;s the case, but i suspect one of the maintainers really depends on steam, or they just like valve. You actually CAN install discord through the void-packages repository, where you can use a tool called xbps-src, that is similar to the AUR (while not being entirely user contributed, it&amp;rsquo;s a very small selection of additional packages from my experience) to install it. Apparently you can also use it to install parsec, but i didn&amp;rsquo;t have any luck with it. Generally it&amp;rsquo;s really confusing. These packages break often and after some time i had to just use the provided tarball for discord / use the browser, which is a bummer. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use discord in the first place but i need it to contact my friends, so you know how it is.
If you want more advanced stuff like ROCm, just forget about it. I don&amp;rsquo;t think you can get blender to use your GPU at all, no matter the vendor. It&amp;rsquo;s not possible on AMD, and it&amp;rsquo;s probably shitty on NVIDIA graphics cards as well. What a shame.
Another thing is also flatpaks were broken on my system, so replacing the often breaking packages from void with their flatpak counterparts (previously mentioned discord, parsec) didn&amp;rsquo;t work, it just made the issue much worse. Flatpak packages on void often had problems with theming, detection of the microphone, file picker issues etc. Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend.
I haven&amp;rsquo;t tried snaps, but they have their own problems so i don&amp;rsquo;t think i should try them anytime soon. Generally the OS can gather bitrot pretty quickly without maintenance due to broken packages etc. It&amp;rsquo;s the only rolling release that made me actually cautious of updating the OS after a while. In most systems like arch i could update after 2 months of not upgrading anything and it would work reasonably well, sadly that isn&amp;rsquo;t the case with Void. I often would have to switch desktop environments because of breakages, and while at the start i used GNOME 40 / 41 (i don&amp;rsquo;t remember exactly), at the end i used MATE, and used almost everything from KDE to window managers and XFCE. Void acts like Windows Millenium in a way, just gathering bugs quicker than it should.
I need to also criticize the Void team a little bit. Their documentation is awful and it&amp;rsquo;s nearly empty. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t contain any information regarding actually installing packages an such, only general stuff and a quick XBPS tutorial. It&amp;rsquo;s a far cry from resources like the arch or gentoo wiki, which are much more helpful despite not being made with void linux in mind. The worst thing is that previously there was a Void Linux wiki, that was probably much better and it actually did contain useful information. Sadly they closed it i think. Now all you get is a simple &amp;ldquo;Void Linux Docs&amp;rdquo; page that contains as much info as an Apple quick start guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-conclusion&#34;&gt;The Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wrap up my rant, i&amp;rsquo;m going to say that void is a really fast distro and it&amp;rsquo;s generally usable for those who want a Linux for their secondary machine (a laptop, old pc etc.), it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunately not suitable for a main production system, and it lacks many important packages that people use every day on other distributions. Runit - while fast - lacks important info and can be confusing. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend it over something like openrc that is almost just as fast with parallelization enabled. If you want a &amp;ldquo;do it yourself&amp;rdquo; linux just get arch or something else, void&amp;rsquo;s not worth your time until they fix these problems, and a few more. Sorry for being a downer i guess.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>FOrg - writing *NIX-style utilities in C</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/forg/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Jul 2023 19:48:15 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/forg/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hi, sorry for my absence, and a long break.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the course of the last month or so i have worked on a file organizer program in C that would fit in with the GNU / BSD Utils. All in 254 lines of code and 190-something SLOC according to github.
I made it with the purpose of learning POSIX APIs and some GNU ones like &lt;em&gt;getopt&lt;/em&gt;. Also i wanted to write something to aid me with my desktop full of icons and other stuff. Before we begin, i&amp;rsquo;d like to say that i&amp;rsquo;m not a professional, or even a semi-professional programmer. My code absolutely sucks and if someone asked me to write &amp;ldquo;FizzBuzz&amp;rdquo; in javascript i would spectacularly fail (probably because i don&amp;rsquo;t know anything about javascript).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-programming&#34;&gt;The Programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first i thought that was easy, since i&amp;rsquo;m relatively knowledgable with C and programmed for Linux for 3 years. I started with a typical &amp;ldquo;Hello world!&amp;rdquo; and a getopt while loop to parse command-line arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#include &amp;#34;stdio.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;stdlib.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;ctype.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;dirent.h&amp;#34; 
#include &amp;#34;string.h&amp;#34;

#include &amp;#34;sys/types.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;sys/stat.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;errno.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;unistd.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;fcntl.h&amp;#34;
#include &amp;#34;getopt.h&amp;#34;

int main(int argc, char *argv[]) {

	while((opt = getopt(argc, argv, &amp;#34;:h?&amp;#34;)) != -1) {

		switch(opt)  {

			case &amp;#39;h&amp;#39;:
				showhelp();
				return 0;
				break;
			case &amp;#39;?&amp;#39;:
				printf(&amp;#34;Unknown option: %c\n&amp;#34;, optopt);
				break;
			case &amp;#39;:&amp;#39;:
				printf(&amp;#34;Missing arg for %c\n&amp;#34;, optopt);
				break;
		} 
	} 

	/* optind is for the extra arguments  which are not parsed */
	for(int index = optind; index &amp;lt; argc; index++ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; flags.verbose != 0){     
		printf(&amp;#34;extra arguments: %s\n&amp;#34;, argv[optind]);
	}
     
	return 0;

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notice the included libraries i have used. previously mentioned &amp;ldquo;getopt&amp;rdquo; is the GNU library for CLI options. sys/types.h and sys/stat.h are POSIX libraries for file management and manipulation.
POSIX also provides the unistd.h library, basically the unix standard library. We also have some classics like stdio, stdlib and string.h which i&amp;rsquo;m using for file path manipulation and listing.
Now i&amp;rsquo;m going to complain a little bit about getopt, specifically it&amp;rsquo;s variable option buffer system that isn&amp;rsquo;t really intuitive and requires you to do at least some RTFM to understand what&amp;rsquo;s happening/ Basically there is an &amp;ldquo;option pointer&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;optind&amp;rdquo;, the arguments are stored in &amp;ldquo;optopt&amp;rdquo; and the state of getopt is stored in &amp;ldquo;opt&amp;rdquo;. These variables are predeterminedand can&amp;rsquo;t be easily changed without modifying getopt itself. I have found out about them by looking up multiple getopt tutorials since i couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a mention of them on the manual page or stack overflow. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s just me being bad at reading, but it was one of my first big hurdles in writing this project.
The next thing i couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure out was printing something if no argument was passed into the program (in this case just &lt;code&gt;./forg&lt;/code&gt;), in fact i still haven&amp;rsquo;t figured that out since there was no information on it online, and every forum post etc. about it was talking about the &lt;code&gt;getopts&lt;/code&gt; command being used in bash scripts.
Okay, enough complaining about GNU libs, time for the real meat.
The next thing i did was making a small clone of &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;, listing files in a directory both recursively and non-recursively. Haven&amp;rsquo;t encountered problems there, and also i have learned a lot about things like UNIX permissions from under the hood. My code thankfully worked as intended, so i moved on to recognizing file formats and sorting files by their type (image, audio, text, other stuff etc.). That was my biggest challenge since i could implement that with multiple different techniques:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use a mime file type file included in most systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use a configuration file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use a lookup table&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;something else, probably&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first i wanted to parse file types from the mime globs file, but later i have realized that on servers and embedded systems things like this don&amp;rsquo;t exist, since they come as a part of desktop environments like Gnome or KDE. So while i already did 75% of the work, i scrapped that idea and decided to use a normal lookup table containing all of the formats mapped to their specific type codes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;0&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;text files, pdf documents etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;videos&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;everything else (projects for specific software, binary files etc.) would go in the &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo; category.
This system thankfully worked flawlessly, and combined with my file listing code it specified a file&amp;rsquo;s format and category. The main advantage of using a built-in lookup table in the code is it working on every system with the program in a binary form. No config files or unnecesary dependencies needed. The only thing the host needs is the core set of utilities like busybox to move files using the mv command, which is invoked by forg (i know it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t and it&amp;rsquo;s bad code, but using a well-coded util is better to implement something myself with a ton of bugs. It&amp;rsquo;s just safer to use popen and leave the sorting to forg).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also i have implemented sorting by filename, where every file including the token in it&amp;rsquo;s name is moved to the appropriate folder, for example &amp;ldquo;bmw-m3.png&amp;rdquo; will be moved into the &amp;ldquo;bmw&amp;rdquo; directory, while something like &amp;ldquo;porsche-911.jpeg&amp;rdquo; won&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-purpose-epilogue&#34;&gt;The purpose (epilogue?)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m happy that forg (at least i think) works as intended and does what i wanted without issue, and developing this little side-project helped me immensely in understanding the UNIX architecture and system calls. For the next few weeks i will focus on improving FOrg and cleaning up it&amp;rsquo;s messy code, maybe even i&amp;rsquo;ll get it into under 200 lines of source. I&amp;rsquo;m going to also focus on documenting it, making a GTK / Qt GUI and maybe even port it to Windows operating systems.
Also to those that think it should be a bash script, make one. I dare you :3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ItzShittyPaper/forg&#34;&gt;https://github.com/ItzShittyPaper/forg&lt;/a&gt;
Bye. See you in whenever i decide to post again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Why design is important in the Free Software space.</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/oss_design/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 20:30:49 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/oss_design/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hi, i came back from the dead again!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So recently i&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about the design of various FOSS programs, and why do i think they&amp;rsquo;re ugly. Here i&amp;rsquo;m going to mostly focus on GIMP, Ardour and Krita, but i&amp;rsquo;ll also show some TUI (terminal / ncurses) programs for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people will agree that FOSS software tends to look worse than it&amp;rsquo;s proprietary counterparts. GIMP looks worse than Photoshop, Kdenlive looks worse than Resolve etc.
There are a ton of reasons why that&amp;rsquo;s the case, but i&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the most important one really. And that is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;made-by-programmers-for-programmers&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;made by programmers, for programmers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact is that programmers are engineers by trait, designers aren&amp;rsquo;t.
In a traditional software company, developers program a feature in, and then a team of designers decide how it will be actually presented for the end user. You know, sketches / concept art, mockups, design systems and other stuff. Finally after a ton of brainstorming and a rigorous testing process the final design gets sent back to the dev team and gets implemented for the release.
Let&amp;rsquo;s compare that to how a FOSS project is developed:
A feature is developed and pushed into the beta branch in the repo, and then random, mostly unexperienced people test it before release. Since everything is implemented by a few programmers, the entire feature is very rough around the edges. The few remaining bugs are fixed in the course of a few days. The design is later tacked on at the end and the entire feature gets pushed into the main branch.
The design usually is still bad and full of unnecessary distractions, so it gets polished in the next major release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in, for example, Photoshop, a feature can get introduced a year later than in it&amp;rsquo;s main FOSS competitor, GIMP, and still be as usable due to the slower design pace of free software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;toolkit-bonanza&#34;&gt;toolkit bonanza&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the functional side of design, there are also aesthetics and themeing.
Most FOSS projects use common UI toolkits like GTK or Qt, so themeing is mostly dependent on the toolkit used. This is especially problematic on Linux, where the user can specify a global GTK or Qt theme to be used in all applications. While this option is useful for simple programs like PDF viewers (and others), and makes programs consistent, it isn&amp;rsquo;t very effective for advanced applications, sometimes breaking widgets and messing with colour palletes. Another gripe i have with this feature that a custom theme literally replaces the application&amp;rsquo;s design system, completely disregarding designer&amp;rsquo;s vision for the software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;imagine if FL Studio used adwaita&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/oss_design/fl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;this is not adwaita tho&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;this is not adwaita tho, it&amp;rsquo;s somehow even worse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really mostly a GTK problem, since Qt does themeing way better by allowing specific programs (like Krita or Kdenlive for example) to override the system Qt theme and also separating the Qt Color Scheme from the theme, theoretically allowing users to use custom color schemes independently from the rest of the application, limiting the potential jankiness, or sometime even eleminating it completely. GTK does not have this though, so you&amp;rsquo;re stuck with your system theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common thing that software developers do to avoid this, is forking the toolkit and building a custom version of it - often with it&amp;rsquo;s own themeing engine - for the project. Im mostly going to reference ardour with this article, since it&amp;rsquo;s a perfect example of a badly done custom toolkit, which hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated in years, and barely works (in my opinion).
At first glance ardour seems like an ideal application when it comes to open-source design, it&amp;rsquo;s consistent, has a custom toolkit and has it&amp;rsquo;s own design language. Also it&amp;rsquo;s very customizable letting you change the color scheme, the transparency of most UI elements, the button style, volume meter style etc. The problem begins when you start actually using it. The first thing most people are going to notice is that some parts of ardour are at best questionable when it comes to design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/oss_design/ardour_screen.png&#34; alt=&#34;the audio connections panel&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;that &amp;lsquo;audio connections&amp;rsquo; panel is really misaligned and generally not suitable for small displays, also it requires a ton of resizing to even see some of the connections. i would personally just use a catia-style patchbay thing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can nitpick weird font choices, misaligned buttons etc. but that&amp;rsquo;s not the point. Instead im going to focus on the toolkit itself, which is mainly GTK+2, but mishmashed with Qt and some other custom widgets. GTK2 itself is deprecated and isn&amp;rsquo;t really used for years now. While i don&amp;rsquo;t have a problem with that, it&amp;rsquo;s unmaintained even by the Ardour team itself. I can only describe the GTK2 foundation as a huge technical debt wearing a &amp;ldquo;skeumorphism nice&amp;rdquo; mask. &lt;em&gt;i said that as a person that loves skeumorphic designs.&lt;/em&gt;
Examples like these can be seen in most semi-professional FOSS software projects, like GIMP - where at the default scale the icons on the bottom of the right sidebar are cut off and not really clear to the user. But really who does it right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-a-good-gui-should-look-like-on-all-platforms&#34;&gt;how a good GUI should look like (on all platforms)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blender.&lt;/em&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/oss_design/blender.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;this is how blender looks like&#34;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But really, blender is a perfect example of good FOSS design.
While people in some 3D / CGI circles don&amp;rsquo;t like blender because of it&amp;rsquo;s design being rooted in the late 90s, and not being refactored in the terms of workflow since then, i can&amp;rsquo;t say it is worse than big projects like 3D Studio Max or Cinema 4D. The team at Blender Foundation did a stellar job at reworking the look and feel of the program in Blender 2.8, making it comparable (or even better) to some proprietary programs.
The layout is clear, easy to understand, AND customizable at the same time, the tabs (while being mostly for show in the default workspace) can help immensely when working, the UI has it&amp;rsquo;s clear and distinct visual style. This is how a profrssional software project should look like. No exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FOSS projects tend to have bad design, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be the case. More people in the community should start focusing on it, improving the experience and promoting the project at the same time. I also would like to see hobbyist designers work on open-source software, submitting designs and making small adjustments.
Ok it&amp;rsquo;s like 1am, it&amp;rsquo;s eepy time. Bye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Sneed&#39;s Feed and Seed</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/sneed/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 09:36:26 +0100</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/sneed/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Formerly Chuck&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;btw the site is back up, with some changes and quality of life improvements&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened&#34;&gt;What happened?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;im planning on releasing a satirical tech news site one day, currently working on it.
i&amp;rsquo;ll make a post about it in a few weeks
also im working on a vidya game, and that shit takes a ton of time i guess&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this place is a huge burden on me really, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to update, the codebase is shit and i don&amp;rsquo;t really have much to say, so there are like 4 posts a year. that means that even IF someone sees this, they&amp;rsquo;ll think that the site is dead and no one works on it anymore. the thing is when i closed it many people online wondered where it went, so i couldn&amp;rsquo;t just leave it like that. so here it is again. have fun!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>my stuff or smthn: The FemboyOS Logo</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/femboyos/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:10:05 +0100</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/femboyos/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;So, i was tasked with designing and making the FembyoOS logo, here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/femboyOS.png&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>You DON&#39;T NEED a good PC</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/goodpc/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 21:47:40 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/goodpc/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s a simple way to have more money. for free!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-do-you-need&#34;&gt;What do you need?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we need to specify how we use computers.
Here are some of the more performance-heavy things that people use PCs for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audio / Video / Image Editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gaming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Browsing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text Editing / Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You probably could do all of these things on a 400$ box.
But how?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lower-you-expectations&#34;&gt;Lower you expectations.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, really.
The most important thing is to lower your expectations and stop fearing change.
You need to basically realize that you don&amp;rsquo;t need to play -  i don&amp;rsquo;t know, Soyberpunk 2077 with raytracing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But don&amp;rsquo;t fear, it is almost always the programmers fault!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let&amp;rsquo;s take Minecraft.
The OG edition of the game is written in java.
Because it was written in java in 2009, the game code runs mostly single-threaded and isn&amp;rsquo;t optimized.
When microsoft decided to make an UWP version of minecraft for windows 10, the xbox and mobile devices - they decided to rewrite the engine in C++.
The results are that in the java version of the game, the max. world render distance is 64 (with optimization mods!).
In the C++ version it&amp;rsquo;s the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it&amp;rsquo;s a small issue compared to&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;muh-heckin-web-browsers11&#34;&gt;mUh HeCkIn WeB bRoWsErS1!1!!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is safe to say it: the web is beyond repair.
The sites are bloated, the browsers are bloated, the languages are bloated.
EVERYTHING. IS. BLOATED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I genuinely think that without a decent PC you can&amp;rsquo;t browse the internet comfortably.
For example, Firefox starts up on my PC (it&amp;rsquo;s pretty beefy, even if the OS is installed on an HDD) in around 5 - 10 seconds.
In comparison - starting up Firefox on my Thinkpad x230 takes 30 seconds.
The worst thing is that there aren&amp;rsquo;t any browsers that are really faster and have good website support, and chromium has the same issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(yes, i know that surf exists, dont @ me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if web browsers were more optimized, they would still have high system requirements due to the web technologies themselves.
Websites really shouldn&amp;rsquo;t compile 25 megabytes of javascript.
If your site requires javascript to function - it probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a website.
Web developers should focus more on stripping down the javascript, not on making the site unusable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;so-how-to-actually-have-a-better-pc-for-free&#34;&gt;So how to actually have a better PC for free&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install linux&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it is required, and you won&amp;rsquo;t escape from it.
You can play almost every game on linux already (from my experience), so there aren&amp;rsquo;t any reasons to not jump ship.
Windows always was the most bloated OS on the market, and it&amp;rsquo;s mere existence is constantly pushing hardware manufacturers to release overpriced, power-hungry CPU&amp;rsquo;s and GPU&amp;rsquo;s.
As for my recommendation - if you want a huge performance boost, just install linux. I would suggest Linux Mint MATE edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(OPTIONAL) Install BSD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you got the balls to do it. do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize your OS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;on windows you really can&amp;rsquo;t truly optimize your system, so i&amp;rsquo;ll just explain what to do on UNIX-based systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install a more lightweight graphical environment.
For example if you use KDE, install XFCE. If you use XFCE, install a tiling window manager etc.
Configuring a tiling WM can be hard, but it will always be way faster than GNOME / KDE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you don&amp;rsquo;t mind wayland you could even use (for gaming) the gamescope compositor made by valve for the steam deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove unnecessary services running in the background
Get rid of plymouth, sshd and other stuff you don&amp;rsquo;t need, you could theoretically not use a display manager and instead use cli login with .bashrc xorg autostart.
It will basically save you ram, and maybe even CPU usage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop running other aplications while gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will greatly increase availible RAM.
Needed for 4GB (or less) ram systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lower your resolution in games (if you can)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD&amp;rsquo;s FSR works on linux without any problems (you can enable it via lutris or in gamescope). if you have a 1920x1080 screen you could just upscale from 1280x720 or 1600x900.
It will increase performance with little loss of visual quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t enable the FPS counter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a little psychological trick.
Just stop caring about the FPS and find the settings that you could play on, without setting the barrier to 60 fps or 30.
Most people could probably play comfortably in 48 fps, and in some games even 24 fps without even knowing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(OPTIONAL) Sell your PC and buy &amp;ldquo;a better one&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds stupid, but with experience you could buy some way better parts for the same price.
You could basically in a few weeks get a 20 - 50% performance boost just by picking your PC parts better.
Also you can just add a couple of bucks to your budget and buy a objectively better computer with a very small price increase (let&amp;rsquo;s say 20 - 50$).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;start-using-software-that-actually-cares-about-performance&#34;&gt;Start using software that actually cares about performance.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a ton of FOSS software that runs a lot better than all of it&amp;rsquo;s proprietary counterparts.
You&amp;rsquo;d be suprised that you could edit videos, do VFX, produce music and code comfortably on a 250$ box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of such software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D / VFX software:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Natron&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video Editors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kdenlive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Olive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoutcut&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handbrake (a media transcoding program)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music Production software / plugins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ardour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OpenMPT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Milkytracker&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calf Plugins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux Studio Plugins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claudia Patchbay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carla Rack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graphics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GIMP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inkscape (for vector graphics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Krita (for drawing and 2D animation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code Blocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VS Codium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vim (dont beat me it&amp;rsquo;s a joke)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When i built my home server, it had a shit GPU (and 7$ Nvidia NVS 300)
I found out that even then it had decent performance in games like Half-Life 2 or Xonotic.
This inspired me to make that article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use your 10 dollar PCs, install gentoo and have fun getting max performance out from you computers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Linux gets Rusty: My Response</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxrust/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 20:55:32 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxrust/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;all i can say is: Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;oxidization&#34;&gt;Oxidization&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;first, we need to look at the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is a new multi-paradigm programming language now commonly used for desktop applications and utilities.
It&amp;rsquo;s biggest &amp;ldquo;pros&amp;rdquo; are efficiency and memory safety.
For context i will just add that Rust is popular among the software development community.
Especially the more &amp;ldquo;Leftist&amp;rdquo; side of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux is implementing Rust simply because there aren&amp;rsquo;t as many C developers as one would think.
Most senior developers working on low-level code are now retired - or dead.
Every year people are stepping down from the kernel and moving on with their lives.
Basically - C is a dead language that zoomers are too afraid to learn, and the supply of people programming in it is quickly depleting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;blahaj-programmer-socks-and-rust&#34;&gt;Blahaj, Programmer Socks, and Rust&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s debunk Rust into oblivion, shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust is more efficient than its biggest competitor, C++ - at least in most cases.
It&amp;rsquo;s mostly because unlike C++ it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have garbage collection.
Instead it uses the concepts of &lt;em&gt;ownership&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;borrowing&lt;/em&gt;.
Ownership basically is a system in which memory is automatically freed when a variable is not needed.
This generally saves memory space, but increases CPU usage and can lead to some other problems.
In C, developer does this manually with the &lt;code&gt;free()&lt;/code&gt; function. Even if this is not needed in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, C is much faster, and modern C compilers can compile memory leak-less code without much trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Memory Safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust fanboys think that it&amp;rsquo;s 100% memory safe. And it&amp;rsquo;s a lie.
Rust in no way guarantees memory safety.
The only difference between &amp;ldquo;unsafe&amp;rdquo; languages like C and rust, is that the Rust compiler flags unsafe code as errors that you need to correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-meme-debunk&#34;&gt;BONUS Meme debunk:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eVeRyThInG iS gOiNg To Be ReWrItTeN iN rUsT!!1!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rust isn&amp;rsquo;t nearly as universal as most femboys on hacker news think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++ iS dEd!!!!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nah, people will still use C++ because of legacy compatibility and a ton C / C++ libraries that will never be usable with other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-kernel-of-c&#34;&gt;The &lt;em&gt;kernel&lt;/em&gt; of C&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, &lt;strong&gt;EXPERIMENTAL&lt;/strong&gt; Rust support is being added to the upcoming linux 6.1 release.
Most distributions will include Rust maybe in a year or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them will probably disable Rust support for some time after the 6.1 release, as it is currently optional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;if-it-moves-compile-it&#34;&gt;If It Moves, Compile It&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My biggest critic of Rust in the kernel is the time it takes to compile.
Another language in the build toolchain will basically make the kernel twice as heavy to run and build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux was historically a very lightweight kernel, despite of it&amp;rsquo;s monolithic nature.
Now it is becoming more and more bloated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned this in my previous blog post, but corporate sponsors are one of the main reasons things like Rust get included in the kernel.
In a few years many people with low-end hardware will probably need to change their setup because of this change (and many others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, sticking to facts: soon compiling the kernel will take around 8 hours on mid-range hardware. imagine using gentoo with these compile times!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;but-should-you&#34;&gt;But Should You?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for now i&amp;rsquo;ll try use linux even with all of this.
but in the future? i will probably switch to BSD.
even without some games, i should be fine with the linux binary compatibility.
idk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Datadesk: What is it?</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/datadesk/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 22:03:49 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/datadesk/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;The worst document format that exists, and why i made it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-tell-me-what-the-fuck-is-it&#34;&gt;But tell me: What the fuck is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Datadesk (DS) is an interpreted markup language that bridges the gap between images and text files.
Characters and sentences are placed by the user on a matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DS has 4 main commands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/s - writes a sentence to the screen, automatically placing multiple lines until the end of the command (/e).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/r - draws a rectangle on the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/e - ends the /s command (and every command that has a dynamic argument number).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;/  - used only once, &amp;ldquo;/&amp;rdquo; means the scene root in a datadesk source file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a line numbering argument for /s evoked by the letter &amp;ldquo;L&amp;rdquo; like this: &lt;code&gt;/sL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language uses a pass-based syntax in which the return key separates different passes.
This approach makes writing software with datadesk in mind really easy.
It works like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1st pass: the y coordinate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2nd pass: the x coordinate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3rd pass: the command / a character&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the 3rd pass is a command there are arguments after the pass; Technically these are called &amp;ldquo;Optional passes&amp;rdquo;.
The y coordinate is specified first because ncurses works the same way.
Even if it feels weird at first, it is really simple in the long run.
This decision makes sense because people first specify the row (y), and then the column (x).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-drawer-interpreter&#34;&gt;The DRAWER interpreter.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DRAWER (DRAWER Reference Alpha-stage Working without Errors and it&amp;rsquo;s Robust as fuck) interpreter, is a ncurses based DS interpreter made by me from scratch.
Currently it only has around 200 lines of code and it&amp;rsquo;s extremely minimal. You can use DRAWER with the following command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;drawer &amp;lt;path to the ds source file.ds&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The document is shown after the execution of that command, you can close the interpreter with F12.
&lt;code&gt;drawer -h&lt;/code&gt; shows you the version of drawer and cli arguments that you can use with it.
&lt;code&gt;drawer -d&lt;/code&gt; shows you a datadesk demo file containing some nice art, graphics etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;datadesk-the-sequel-what-will-follow-ds1&#34;&gt;Datadesk: The sequel (what will follow DS1?)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m currently planning on adding support on multiple pages in the same document and adding variables.
Maybe i will do things such as block quotes and support for slanted and bold text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DS3 will probably have some interactive elements added as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened-to-your-previous-project-allcom&#34;&gt;What happened to your previous project, allcom?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lost motivation and cancelled the game. That&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Linux is dead (and we killed it)</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxsucks/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 21:57:30 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxsucks/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Look, it&amp;rsquo;s just my opinion. But Linux is truly dead.
It has become unstable, bloated and unusable. Even Windows beats most popular distros in that regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even &amp;ldquo;pro&amp;rdquo; distributions like Arch or Gentoo suffer from most of the problems that modern UNIX has.
An example that i like to use is NetworkManager, a truly useless piece of software.
This deamon really is just a workaround that makes systemd&amp;rsquo;s network system usable to your average Joe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other init-systems like openrc and runit just work.
Yes - they require a dhcp service (if you even use dhcp) - but even then these init systems ship with at least working network setup tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s analyze the downfall of Linux in detail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-desktop&#34;&gt;The Desktop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me it all started with GNOME 3.
I know I sound stupid because everyone bullies GNOME and systemd, but hear me out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GNOME 2 was perfect.
Ok, maybe not. Still it was really close to perfection. Why?
It was easy to use, stable and customizable - everything you want from a desktop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, from nowhere - gnome 3 appeared.
They have scrapped everything they built since the 90s and started from scratch.
And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a success, actually, it was the Windows Vista of linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone came to my house with a gun and said &amp;ldquo;describe what gnome 3 in 2011 was in 5 seconds or i&amp;rsquo;ll shoot you&amp;rdquo; i would say that it was janky, very janky.
I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand why the dev-team did this, and i don&amp;rsquo;t understand it now.
After some time the GNOME team fixed their desktop, and it was actually pretty easy to use.
Most popular distributions like ubuntu returned to their roots with shipping gnome again.
But while all of this was happening, gnome 3 was the literal definition of a &amp;ldquo;dumpster fire&amp;rdquo; under the hood.
Through time the team added too many unneceseary features to gnome and added systemd dependencies.
Because of the popularity of systemd, no one saw this as a problem. But it really is.
Now with GNOME 42 using 2 gigs idling i can confortably say that it won&amp;rsquo;t ever go back to it&amp;rsquo;s days of glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KDE had gone a simillar route, but with a happier ending overall.
KDE 3 was the best alternative to GNOME 2, and the most customizable desktop of it&amp;rsquo;s time.
In 2008 / 2009 KDE 4 was released. And you guessed it - it was a total disaster.
Everybody hated this thing, it was barely usable. At least GNOME 3 didn&amp;rsquo;t crashed almost every time you wanted to change a theme.
The succesor to KDE 4, Plasma is actually very successful to this day. It mostly reclaimed the desktop throne from KDE 3 / Trinity, and it is the favourite to this day.
But it didn&amp;rsquo;t protect KDE from it&amp;rsquo;s jank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;kde-plasma-jank-list&#34;&gt;KDE Plasma jank list&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a ton of confusing menus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QT5 is still a mess&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses even more ram than GNOME&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outdated widgets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature Creep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weird Design Choices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A shitty store app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broken, unfinished app suite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breeze theme is the only one that is actually usable and integrates with GTK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unpolished, buggy animations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bugs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bugs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even More Bugs!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, let&amp;rsquo;s end it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;systemd&#34;&gt;systemd&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the other side of our linux coin is &lt;strong&gt;systemd&lt;/strong&gt;, a linux init system that creeped into every distro since Debian 7 codenamed &amp;ldquo;Jessie&amp;rdquo;
Most people just don&amp;rsquo;t care enough about linux&amp;rsquo;s internal workings to hate systemd - it is still a usable and easy to use init system.
I know that it&amp;rsquo;s a meme, but systemd really is the most bloated PID1 that ever existed, having a ton of useless services that shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even be there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-not-so-comprehensive-list-of-useless-soystemd-wonk-and-jank&#34;&gt;The not-so comprehensive list of useless soystemd wonk and jank&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-homed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-logind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-boot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd/Journal (yes, there are multiple naming conventions used there)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-sysusers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-nspawn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-stub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd.mount (another naming convention)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;systemd-fstab-generator (WHY, JUST WHY. &lt;code&gt;genfstab&lt;/code&gt; exists.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all of these systemd modules shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a part of the init system, but they somehow are&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from systemd&amp;rsquo;s disregard of the UNIX philosophy, it boots significantly slower than for example runit or s6 (at least on all of my machines).
It is really a beast, a performance hog and it simply just does too much. PID 1 should just start some services with dependency management and that&amp;rsquo;s it.
Another big thing that i hate is &lt;strong&gt;pulseaudio&lt;/strong&gt;, even if it is being currently replaced by pipewire (and that&amp;rsquo;s really good) - it is a wonky mess that never works,
uses too much system resources, isn&amp;rsquo;t system-wide, has horrible command-line interfaces and is just simply buggy.
We should stick to alsa in the long-term. Why?
It simply just works, yes - only after extensive configuration to let it work on modern browsers, add multi-channel support etc. - but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mentality of &lt;em&gt;Lennart Poettering&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; software is spreading too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-freedom-anyway&#34;&gt;What is Freedom anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freedom in linux is decaying.
Most people are forced to use pulseaudio (because of steam and other stuff), X.Org (wayland exists, but it isn&amp;rsquo;t as stable), systemd (because gnome) and other things.
In the early days of linux there really was more choice than now.
In the 90s and early 2000s, when UNIX systems came to your average Joe, people used BSDs, Linuxes, BeOS etc.
Now it&amp;rsquo;s just ubuntu and arch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People started realizing this and now some are moving to BSD or - if someone doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about privacy - MacOS.
I suspect that in a few years most popular linux distros will be closer to windows than to any free-software UNIX imaginable.
But let&amp;rsquo;s end this for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux users wanting it to be more &amp;ldquo;user-friendly&amp;rdquo; killed linux. Yes, it is more integrated - but at what cost?
GNOME 3 and systemd are the greatest examples of this trend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Piracy is 80% morally correct</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/piracy/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 21:51:54 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/piracy/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;this will be a controversial one&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-piracy-stealing&#34;&gt;Is Piracy Stealing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, not at all.
Unlike real piracy (a group of guys goes into a boat in the middle of the fucking ocean and steals everything) nothing just ceases to exist.
So technically it is just unauthorized file copying, which sounds stupid because everyone can copy files on their disk in any capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even then, let&amp;rsquo;s be honest.
Stealing (like real stealing) from big corporations doesn&amp;rsquo;t hurt them much + nobody cares about them (outside of the apple community where apple inc. is their lord and savior).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-that-20&#34;&gt;What about that 20%?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That 20% is mostly stuff that is already illegal, or it&amp;rsquo;s just immoral anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Porn (don&amp;rsquo;t coom kids.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Child Po- Cheese Pizza&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Why would you download this, yes downloading this stuff from torrent with a VPN is safe (kind of) but why?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some indie games made by a guy in his basement worth for five bucks (not talking about AAA&amp;rsquo;s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Like these people actually want to make something good, support them. But still &amp;ldquo;no tux, no bux&amp;rdquo; is a rule that i&amp;rsquo;ll follow.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bittorrent-protocol-itself&#34;&gt;The BitTorrent protocol itself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like torrents mostly because the BitTorrent protocol revolutionized the Internet.
It was created when your average internet connection was around 50 KB/s, and most people still used dial-up.
But why it was so revolutional?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it is very hard to shut down a torrent network - that&amp;rsquo;s why it is so commonly used for piracy and rare / lost media archival.
Back in the day most websites were owned by people, not companies. A side effect of this was that servers of a website could be shut down at any time due to many reasons. The creator of that site could be bored, forgot to turn on his server etc.
Obviously, when the servers are down, you cannot download stuff from this person. BitTorrent is decentralized, so everyone having the file on his own computer is a potential server. Only one person online (more popular torrents have even 50 people at the same time) can keep the torrent up and send the data to you.
Because of this decentralization, most companies can&amp;rsquo;t stop even a single torrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from that, download speeds of the files sent through torrent weren&amp;rsquo;t capped by the server, so these files could be downloaded with very high speeds.
These reasons are all i need to prefer torrent over anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-2-interwebz-pirate&#34;&gt;how 2 interwebz pirate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to know what is a torrent tracker.
A torrent tracker is a server that - as the name suggests - tracks peers across many torrent networks. Most of these trackers are aggregated and hosted on sites like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thepiratebay.org&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1337x.to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rutracker.org (it&amp;rsquo;s in russian, some basic language skills required to use it on a daily basis)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;these are sites that i prefer to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to download files from them? It&amp;rsquo;s easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to the website (example is from thepiratebay.org)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;search what you want&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click on it (and avoid ads when possible)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;click on the button with da magnet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;your client should appear and set up the torrent for you by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relax and wait till the thing completes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;now you have your favourite music album, hentai game, or something else on your hard drive!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ending&#34;&gt;Ending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was it, i hope this guide to torrents was useful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>m4kulatura&#39;s music corner :3</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/music/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 23:06:35 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/music/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;yeah, i make music. nothing really interesting.
started as a small side project, and now it&amp;rsquo;s the main thing i do.
i used almost everything from FL Studio to MOD Trackers like OpenMPT or the OGs like Impulse Tracker and FastTracker II.
here, have some of my albums, some sound bad, some sound good:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/music.css&#34;&gt;
&lt;link rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/blog.css&#34;&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;grid&#34;&gt;

        	&lt;div class=&#34;ibm_cp&#34;&gt;
				
			&lt;p&gt;barber for ducks (2023)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/barber_cover.png&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/cWxGCB4D#yHuWjUD2C-gTMrTsVDB41m4_zsF8deRh9jytw0ZfypI&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;m4kulaturamusic&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;imagine fucking existing (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/imagine_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/BbRRBIAT#VIo1vYz6FdRXh6q2RUu3wa6yuXXXJxBZtLpksSXjHNo&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;tracking&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;Tracking Devices (2021)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/trackingdevices_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/dG4TiaDK#OmE7ubjoY_R1O7QZY7FDNh9E7aY9XHSc6ohTeSd3qDM&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;house&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;Chastity House (2022)&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/chastityhouse_cover.jpg&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt;
			&lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/NXIzBSpQ#Bi1xgvVaHVjRpLa-4ULB5h_0ip0m6Pwx22AMyigjYJY&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&#34;stop&#34;&gt;
		
			&lt;p2&gt;bus stop [EP] (2023)&lt;/p2&gt;
			&lt;img src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/busstop_cover.png&#34; alt=&#34; &#34;&gt; &lt;br&gt;
			&lt;p2&gt;full track, no download required: &lt;/p2&gt; &lt;br&gt;
			&lt;audio controls&gt;
				&lt;source src=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/music/bus_stop.ogg&#34; type=&#34;audio/ogg&#34;&gt;
			&lt;/audio&gt; &lt;br&gt;
			&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/cHgAhB5S#kmPaJDtAYu9TUbIVGCPmqVzOMnwXWHM7gEOj-pHC56I&#34;&gt;Download Link&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;/div&gt;
		
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NOTE: ADD SOME SAMPLES HERE SO PEOPLE WOULD LISTEN TO YOUR SHIT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all of my tracker modules (at the time of writing this) (more free music !!! )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mega.nz/file/JWhyhYTb#R5hu0qFe2qHGO2-njYW-YHgpvR_nM7PH81PPXh8GoQE&#34;&gt;downwoad it uwu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Reserve</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/reserve/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:14:13 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/reserve/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-the-fuck-is-it&#34;&gt;What the fuck is it?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;m4kulatura&amp;rsquo;s private reserve (MPR) is a repository full of software, games, music and other stuff.
it is submitted by m4kulatura and his friends mostly for personal use and archival.
still, anyone with an internet connection can download files from the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;download-as-much-as-you-want&#34;&gt;download as much as you want!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;http server: &lt;a href=&#34;https://ftp.whentheh.tk&#34;&gt;https://ftp.whentheh.tk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(currently inactive due to maintenance)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>M4kulatura</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/m4kulatura/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:01:17 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/m4kulatura/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura is the main character in the m4kulatura lore.
Basically the center-piece connecting everything together.
Working on his webiste and multiple other projects since 2016.
Oh and he also makes music: &lt;a href=&#34;https://makulaturka.tk/music&#34;&gt;https://makulaturka.tk/music&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;info&#34;&gt;Info:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Class: Boomer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sub-Class: Femboy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Age: 14 (as of now)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sex: Male (sadly)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orientation (sowwy fow le LGBT speek ;-;): asexual, heteroromantic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a boyfriend: nope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has a girlfriend: nope. (oficially)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes to work: nope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goes to school: yes, he goes to ZSTiE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;related-to&#34;&gt;Related to:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blueberry (best friend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DeusVult (2nd best friend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynio (coworker / friend)
tty7derty
askel
snybej
przerbek
major
ballie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kosmitek (classmate)
Lewan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matteo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CartoonGuy (an old friend)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sofe (&lt;em&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s a long story&lt;/em&gt; / ex (?) )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura is the main maintainer of projects like WarpOS, TMS, MMS, datadesk and others.
He does it mostly for fun and to let his mind focus on things other than school and work.
Aside from maintaining these systems he has an average social life and composes music in his spare time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura a few years ago started talking to sofe.
They were best friends for a few years, knowing everything about eachother and living their lives together.
Most people said that they were &lt;strong&gt;[REDACTED]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some time they broke up, this breakup caused a suicide attempt involving m4kulatura, as well as other issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M4kulatura also has some controversial, right-wing political opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;likes&#34;&gt;Likes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old Tech&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic Games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Politics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Economics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low-Level Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hates&#34;&gt;Hates:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoomers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TikTok&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proprietary Software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple Stans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LGBT+ Fandom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Furries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;annotations&#34;&gt;Annotations:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;none&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>wiki template</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/template/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:01:17 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/template/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;a basic summary&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;info&#34;&gt;Info:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;related-to&#34;&gt;Related to:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;more detailed info&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;likes&#34;&gt;Likes:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hates&#34;&gt;Hates:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;annotations&#34;&gt;Annotations:&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Wikitest</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wikitest/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 22:01:17 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wikitest/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;esse mam z cb&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/about/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 21:54:15 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/about/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, im m4kulatura, you can contact me on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;email: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:m4kulatura@gmail.com&#34;&gt;m4kulatura@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; (yep, i still use gmail)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discord: cheese thrower#3178&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IRC: currently closed, no irc :C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Soulseek: m4kulatura&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;funni m4k guestbook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://users2.smartgb.com/g/g.php?a=s&amp;amp;i=g26-39103-46&#34;&gt;http://users2.smartgb.com/g/g.php?a=s&amp;amp;i=g26-39103-46&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;oh and here&amp;rsquo;s some info about me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-do-i-use&#34;&gt;what do i use?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OS: Void GNU/Linux 64-bit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desktop: MATE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web Browser: FurryFox (mozilla firefox)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image Editor: GIMP + Krita (for drawing)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video Editor: Blender&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D art / 2D art / VFX: again, Blender&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music Stuff: trackers + Ardour&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text / Code editor: Vim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hardware&#34;&gt;hardware:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cellphone: Samsung Galaxy A13, i fucking hate that phone&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Music Player: my phone, connected to my server running mpd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laptop: Lenovo Thinkpad x230&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Headphones: AKG K712 PRO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microphone: Crono Studio 101 (cheap shit)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keyboard: SPC Gear GK630&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mouse: Glorious Model O and sometimes a Razer Diamondback (original from 2005)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;specs&#34;&gt;specs:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CPU: AMD Ryzen 5 3600&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPU: AMD Radeon 6600 XT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAM: 16GB (2x8) DDR4 3200MHz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HDD / SSD: 500gb SSD; 500gb HDD; 2TB HDD;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Blog</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/blog/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 21:51:55 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/blog/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;My blog, i usually talk about technology, but i do other things as well.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2023-08-05T20:13:52&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2023 Aug 05&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/voidlinux1year/&#34;&gt;Void Linux: a Year long review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2023-07-03T19:48:15&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2023 Jul 03&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/forg/&#34;&gt;FOrg - writing *NIX-style utilities in C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2023-04-26T20:30:49&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2023 Apr 26&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/oss_design/&#34;&gt;Why design is important in the Free Software space.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2023-03-05T09:36:26&amp;#43;01:00&#34;&gt;2023 Mar 05&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/sneed/&#34;&gt;Sneed&amp;#39;s Feed and Seed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-12-30T00:10:05&amp;#43;01:00&#34;&gt;2022 Dec 30&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/femboyos/&#34;&gt;my stuff or smthn: The FemboyOS Logo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-19T21:47:40&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 19&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/goodpc/&#34;&gt;You DON&amp;#39;T NEED a good PC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-10T20:55:32&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 10&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxrust/&#34;&gt;Linux gets Rusty: My Response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-06T22:03:49&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 06&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/datadesk/&#34;&gt;Datadesk: What is it?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-06T21:57:30&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 06&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/linuxsucks/&#34;&gt;Linux is dead (and we killed it)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-10-06T21:51:54&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Oct 06&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/piracy/&#34;&gt;Piracy is 80% morally correct&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>M4kulatura wiki</title>
		<link>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 21:51:55 +0200</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the m4kulatura lore wiki, sadly it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated in a while.
Fortunately i&amp;rsquo;m currently working on it!
Feel free to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-09-22T22:01:17&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Sep 22&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/m4kulatura/&#34;&gt;M4kulatura&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-09-22T22:01:17&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Sep 22&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/wiki/template/&#34;&gt;wiki template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

	&lt;li&gt;&lt;time datetime=&#34;2022-09-22T22:01:17&amp;#43;02:00&#34;&gt;2022 Sep 22&lt;/time&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://zesrajsie.tk/wikitest/&#34;&gt;Wikitest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
